Guide to the Adriaan Jacob Barnouw Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Adriaan Jacob Barnouw Papers,
1895-1967.
Barnouw, Adriaan Jacob, 1877-1968.
6 linear ft (ca. 2,000 items in 13 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078950
Biographical Note
Queen Wilhelmina Professor of the Language and Literature of the Netherlands at Columbia University, 1921-1948.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, speeches, and articles of Barnouw. There is little correspondence in the collection and only a few manuscripts, but a large file of Barnouw's published articles and reviews is included in the papers. In addition, there are incomplete sets of two publications that Barnouw edited, WEEKLY REVIEW (1919-1921) and the NETHERLAND-AMERICA FOUNDATION MONTHLY LETTER (1924-1948, 1954-1961). Several old Dutch documents which had been collected by Barnouw are also in the collection. There is one folder of letters and documents relating to the Frisian Freedom movement during the later years of World War II. Also, Barnouw's manuscript of THE PAGEANT OF NETHERLANDS HISTORY transferred from Authors' Manuscripts Collection.
Arrangement
Selected materials cataloged; remainder arranged.
Subjects
Columbia University--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945--Netherlands--Friesland.; Linguistics.; Dutch literature.; College teachers.
Access Restrictions
Boxes 2-13 of this collection are located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.This collection has no restrictions
Acquisition
12/28/72 M72-12-28
Gift of Elsa Barnouw, 1972.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Barnouw, Adriaan Jacob (Box 1)
  - Jameson. John Franklin (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt. Franklin Delano (Box 1)
  - Turnbull de Mikker, William Pieter (Box 1)
- Series II: Manuscripts, etc.
  - Manuscripts (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts (continued) (Box 2)
  - Speeches (Box 2)
  - Notes (Box 2)
  - Articles and Clippings (Box 2)
  - Articles and Clippings (1926-1967) (Box 3)
  - Writings in Nation (Box 3)
  - The Pageant of Netherlands History -manuscript (Box 4)
  - Netherland-America Foundation Monthly Letter (1924-1936) (Box 5)
  - Netherland-America Foundation Monthly Letter (1937-1948) (Box 6)
  - Weekly Review, January 1920-August 1921 (Box 7)
  - Netherland-America Foundation Monthly Letter (1954-1961) (Box 8)
  - Weekly Review, May-December 1919 (Box 8)
  - Weekly Review (duplicates) (Box 9)
  - Old Dutch documents and manuscripts (Box 9)
  - Photographs (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Books (Box 10)
  - Cartoon Clippings-World Wax I (1917-1919) (Box 11)
  - Manuscripts of other authors (Box 11)
  - Biographical Materials (Box 11)
  - Printed Materials (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous items-Gift of Miss Elsa Barnouw, 1973 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook1973 (Box 13)